hey what's up guys my name is a China
welcome back to my estate bust loss
series so first of all let me just say
huge thank you to all of you for helping
me reach 100,000 subscribers it's been
quite a journey at first on YouTube in
2011 and I guess most seriously in 2012
I'm even more seriously probably at the
start of last year when I stopped at the
cipa Plus series and the OpenGL serie
since has been quite a journey and I
really do feel very thankful and very
blessed to have a hundred thousand
people following this channel so a huge
thank you to all of you and today what
we're going to talk about is just kind
of a bit of a quick visual studio tip
and just a tip in general for
development and for debugging and that's
going to be about breakpoints but not
just about breakpoints if you don't know
what a breakpoint is definitely watch
that video but this isn't just about
normal breakpoints it's going to be
about conditions and actions that we can
apply to breakpoints so by conditions or
conditional breakpoints what I mean is
we can actually tell them to put the
debugger I want to place a breakpoint
here but I only want the breakpoint to
trigger under a certain condition
something in memory basically that's
going to meet my criteria if that's the
case then please trigger this breakpoint
and an actionable break points of action
breakpoints are just something that will
allow us to take some kind of action
generally print something to the console
when a breakpoint is hit so there's kind
of two I guess types of action
breakpoints there's one that let the
lets you kind of just continue execution
while printing what you want so for
example let's just say I wanted to log
the mouse position what I could do is
every time the mouse position is
recorded because like every time I mouse
move move event happens for example I
could have that breakpoint actually
print something to the console but keep
the driver I'm running or I could get it
to like print something to the console
but still break the program's they're
still gonna pause execution of the
program so that we can inspect other
things in memory so again breakpoints in
general make sure you watch that video
because if you're in order break point
is this isn't gonna really help much but
action breakpoints and conditional
breakpoints are really really useful as
kind of a further debugging tool now
everything that you can do with these
breakpoints you can actually do in code
okay I could just write an if statement
for example but check something
and then obviously just put a breakpoint
inside that if statement and if they've
seven is true then the break point will
be tripped all right I don't even have
to put a break point I could just even
write debug break or something like that
some kind of compiler intrinsic that
actually will break the debugger if it's
attached at that given line of code kind
of like what we do with with assertion
mappers that's one possibility and with
action break points again printing
something to the console obviously you
can do that in code but where this
really comes in handy is where we might
have gotten our program into some kind
of state that is a bug perhaps and we
want to inspect certain kind of
properties to figure out what what like
what's caused this bug or like why am I
in this state or what even is this
daylight right like what is my stuff set
to why have why is this happened and
obviously if we were to actually if we
were to actually kind of decide to add
code to our code base but have to
terminate the application and then
recompile it and then that would be an
issue because maybe we couldn't get it
to the stated yeah maybe it was really
difficult to get to state and I mean
generally it will just slow down our
workflow if we have to keep kind of
stopping reconciling out in code like
and then getting up to the state that
led up to like why were like what
exactly we want to debug and all of that
so it's a huge issue and this really
does help us out a lot so let's just
dive into some code whatever here
actually is the source code to Sparky
which is a game engine that I made about
three years ago and then what I want to
do is I'll just launch and kind of show
you guys what we're dealing with this is
just an example project it could be
anything but I thought I'd actually use
kind of a real-world project instead of
just doing something like I don't know
our some kind of weird hello world app
that probably wouldn't show you much so
all we have here is really just is this
scene which has some graphics in and
when I finally opens and then we have
like you know some metal and plastic
balls of various roughnesses and all
that and in fact I think the OpenGL
version or Sparky is a bit not as good
as the DirectX version so there might be
some artifacts but anyway the point is
we have kind of a 3d app here and what I
want to do is while this is running
without actually closing it I'm gonna
I've just decided that I want to debug
the mouse position because the position
the mouse just seems to be a bit wrong
so what I'll do is I'll go to the code
that
surely record amounts position switch in
this case is with win32 input does every
be I'm just closes in the right view to
make some more space and then what I'm
going to do is find the mouth let's just
say the button callback right so every
time a button is clicked this gets
called and we have this kind of mouse
position x and y that gets set here now
I want to debug that so what I'll do is
I'll jump to the end of here and
actually of course I'm not gonna add
code all I'm really gonna do is I'm just
gonna put a breakpoint like on this line
for example I'm gonna right click on
this break point and then go to
conditions okay or in fact well let's
just log at first so we can go to
actions okay and conditions and actions
are both here so we can actually use a
condition and an action together right
you have to click on actions first and
then add a condition to it otherwise it
well we have to actually add something
and then it will let us kind of um do
both but anyway let's start with an
action so we'll log something to the
Apple window and we will decide to
continue execution so the way that we do
this if we have variables that we want
to do and this actually shows you a bit
at the syntax what we can do is just use
curly brackets and inside the curly
brackets we can put in a variable name
such as X or input manager arrow mem
underscore mouse position X or something
like that X is just obviously easier to
write
so we'll do X and you can do things like
cast so it will cost to a float if we
want we don't have to do in this case
it's just going to be an integer Mouse
position so we'd say the value 8 away
properly but I'll cause it to a float is
so fun to show you that you can so x and
y okay so X and then comma Y and you can
see that I'm kind of encompassing these
variable names inside curly brackets and
I can you know add some other text like
the mouse position is that okay and
there we go we have that let's hit close
and the application is still running
obviously so what I'm gonna do is I'm
just gonna click and if we go into our
output window you'll see that it
actually tells us what our mouse
position is and if I drag this up a bit
more so you guys can see and I go back
to my program and I just click all over
the place let me move this in fact I'll
resize it make it smaller you can see
I'm clicking all over the place and it's
telling me what my mouse position is
okay and looks like that whole box being
called twice for some reason
anyway you can say that I have the math
position being printed in real time
while my application is running and I
guess the big takeaway from this is
obviously I could just add code that
prints that in the actual source code of
the application but the cool thing is I
haven't have stopped my application
right I haven't actually had to
recompile any code or anything this is
just while my initial application was
running I've managed to print additional
data to the console the other way of
doing this would be to just add a
regular breakpoint click and then look
at you know the broken program like well
it's paused and look at the variables
but that would be way too long right
yeah I can just click all over the place
literally and you can see I'll just get
all the data I need immediately so it's
really powerful now to test conditions
let's just say that I want my mouse
position to him to be printed under a 7
condition so maybe if X is greater than
500 or something because I know it only
happens on the right side of the screen
so I'll go to my conditions and you can
see I've enabled both conditions and
actions here now I'll just say X square
than 500 okay that's 5,000 X greater
than 500 okay just a conditional
expression can be any boolean statement
and then I'll just close that but
hitting close or just by closing it
there and if I go back you'll see that
if I click on the left side screen
nothing gets printed but it soon as I
click on the right side of screen it
prints my value okay so that's a way for
us to only evaluate breakpoints under a
certain condition and of course if I
come back over here and go to actions
again I can uncheck continue execution
which means that when I actually do
click on the left size frame nothing
happens on the right side of screen
it'll print my value and then also you
can see my program is now paused so that
I can look at all the values I need over
here if I really want to okay so that's
it that's conditions of actions I use
these all the time when I need to
because it's they're just really
powerful and they're just really good
for speeding up your workflow again
nothing you can't do via other means but
it's just if you're in the middle of
something complex especially if you're
working on a large application you know
that shutting it all down recompiling
the kuroda going back it's gonna take
forever and it may not even get you to
the point where you have that bug in
likely you
that program in that reproducible state
for the bug so this is something that is
incredibly useful and everyone should be
using one thing I will say is the
conditions are very very useful for
things like loops if you have an update
loop right like this is a game right so
I have an update loop that's running 60
times per second and I want to cache a
particular condition that's almost
impossible to do with breakpoints like
maybe I'm just kind of traversing this
whole node hierarchy of all my entities
in my game and I have like 5000 entities
and I just want to break on the one
that's called player or the one that's
called enemy 405 right because that's
the problem one well that's going to be
so difficult to do manually you'll put a
breakpoint you'll keep hitting f5 until
you get to the point where the name of
the entity equals you know enemy 405
right but if you put a condition down
which says I'd only activate this
breakpoint if name is enemy 405 well
guess what you've just done that
instantly with absolutely no work I will
say that this slows down your program a
lot so if you keep putting down
conditional breakpoints and actual
breakpoints and all this like in a
real-time application you'll probably
drop to like 5 fps or something like
that it will lag that's just how they
work there's slow but obviously there
are debugging tools so usually that's
not going to affect you too much if you
are worried about performance then just
stop your application recompile it with
some code which handles us for you
instead of using the debugger for that
because having the debugger attached and
doing this is quite slow anyway I hope
you guys enjoyed this video if you did
you can hit the like button you can
follow me on Twitter and Instagram as
well to get updates about all my videos
and stuff like that
patriarchal course after Jenner is the
best way to support this series and this
YouTube channel so thank you so much to
all of my patrons which make this series
possible in the next video we're going
to be talking about some more visual
studio debugging features that I want to
kind of introduce because we're gonna be
starting some other series soon it's
gonna be pretty big and I want everyone
to be kind of comfortable with Visual
Studio and what's it all spots to the
point where we can debug our code
effectively thank you guys for watching
I'll see you next time goodbye
[Music]